{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "During this campaign, the city of Camarina declared its neutrality but secretly sent arms to Hermocrates. A war between the cities of Selinus and Segesta was used as pretext for this campaign, which ominously began with the destruction of sacred hermai statues; that crime was falsely blamed on Alcibiades, who then defected rather than face trial. For ten points, name this disastrous campaign of the Peloponnesian War in which an Athenian force was completely wiped out on a large Mediterranean island.",
      "answer": [
        "Sicilian Expedition",
        "descriptions of Athens’ invasion of Sicily"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. Thomas Graham led diplomatic efforts in support of this goal, which was discussed at the Pugwash Conferences. A 1968 treaty with 3 “pillars” sought this goal, which enjoyed a significant step forward with the INF treaty signed after the Reykjavik Summit. Treaties like SALT and START sought, for ten points, what peaceful goal regarding a certain type of dangerous weapon?",
      "answer": [
        "nuclear disarmament",
        "nuclear nonproliferation",
        "anything related to reducing the number of nuclear weapons"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This god burned himself to death after he slept with a celibate priestess while drunk. This god contributed his own blood to create the fifth world-cycle, and supposedly invented books and the calendar. This brother of Xolotl [sho-LOT-ull] was identified with Venus and, supposedly, also with the conquistador Hernan Cortes when he arrived in Mexico in 1519. For ten points, name this Aztec God who fought with Tezcatlipoca, a feathered serpent.",
      "answer": "Quetzalcoatl"
    },
    {
      "question": "While serving on an expedition for Alonso de Ojeda, this man decided to split and sail southward, during which time he discovered the mouth of the Amazon River. In 1508, Ferdinand II of Aragon commissioned this man to be chief navigator of Spain. This man was the first to notice that the New World was separate from Asia, inspiring Martin Waldseemuller to adopt his name for certain landmasses on a map. For ten points, name this explorer who lends his name to two continents.",
      "answer": "Amerigo Vespucci"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man rose to his highest post after Milan Gorkic was assassinated by secret police. He emerged victorious in a power struggle with Draza Mihailovic’s Chetniks. This man was eventually expelled from Cominform after his style of socialism led to a break with Joseph Stalin, so he instead served as the European leader of the Non-Aligned movement. For ten points, name this marshal who led Yugoslavia following World War II.",
      "answer": "Josip Broz Tito"
    },
    {
      "question": "The land for a colony in this modern-day state was possibly bought after thirteen coats were given to the Quinnipiack tribe by Theophilus Eaton and John Davenport. A university in this state was previously located in the nearby town of Saybrook; that Ivy League institution formed in 1701 amidst clerical differences in the faculty at Harvard. For ten points, name this state, home to Yale University and the 1815 Hartford Convention.",
      "answer": "Connecticut"
    },
    {
      "question": "Scenes of this people’s daily life and armed conflict are among subject matter of paintings found in the Franc¸ois tomb. Cosimo de Medici bought a famous bronze statue of made by these people depicting a chimera. The prevalence of horse figurines in the Villanovan culture suggests their importance to these people, who lived in cities like Tarquinia and Veii. Present-day Umbria and Tuscany was home to, for ten points, what Italian people who fought a series of wars with ancient Rome?",
      "answer": "Etruscans"
    },
    {
      "question": "A precursor to this object used by FDR was called Sacred Cow. Mark Tillman once controlled this object, which one man was forced to use after giving a speech at an elementary school in Sarasota, Florida. Golden livery in this object was designed with the help of Jackie Kennedy, who was present when Lyndon Johnson was sworn in aboard it. John F. Kennedy’s body was taken to Washington D.C. on, for ten points, what aircraft that transports the President?",
      "answer": "Air Force One"
    },
    {
      "question": "Raising awareness of this disease was the goal of the VDRP, an American media campaign. It has been theorized that Christopher Columbus’s crewmen brought this disease to Europe from the New World. The progression of this disease was studied in people with “bad blood” even after the discovery of penicillin, a suitable antibiotic for this disease. Researchers at the Tuskegee Institute carried out unethical experimentation on African American men who were given, for ten points, what sexually-transmitted disease?",
      "answer": "syphilis"
    },
    {
      "question": "Concerns that she was too young for marriage may have prompted one member of this family to break off her engagement to the playwright Royall Tyler; that woman from this family was nicknamed “Nabby.” Another member of this family served as minister to the Netherlands during the Washington administration, helping John Jay negotiate his namesake treaty. That man from this family traveled with his father on a diplomatic journey to France in 1778 and was born in Quincy, Massachusetts. For ten points, name this early American family that included the second and sixth presidents.",
      "answer": "Adams family"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire came to power after throwing off the yoke of the Kaniaga kingdom of the Sosso peoples. This empire appointed farbins to rule over conquered lands and referred to its territories as the “Twelve Doors.” This empire’s victory at the 13th century Battle of Kirina over Sumanguru allowed this empire to rule much of Africa. Sankore University became a madrassa under, for ten points, what west African empire that was eventually supplanted by the Songhai and once ruled by Mansa Musa?",
        "answer": "Mali Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This “Lion of Mali” won the Battle of Kirina, founded the Mali Empire, and was an older relative of Mansa Musa.",
        "answer": [
          "Mansa Sundiata Keita",
          "either",
          "both"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A popular dime novel referred to this woman as “The White Devil of the Yellowstone.” A first-hand account claimed that the rescue of Captain Egan at Goose Creek inspired this woman’s nickname. Jean McCormick claimed to be the daughter of this woman who allegedly chased after Jack McCall with a meat cleaver after he killed Wild Bill Hickok. For ten points, name this American frontierswoman and storyteller in Buffalo Bill’s Wild West Show.",
        "answer": [
          "Calamity Jane",
          "Martha Jane Canary"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Calamity Jane was buried next to Wild Bill Hickok in this South Dakota town, where Hickok was shot.",
        "answer": "Deadwood"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler’s forces were victorious at the Battle of Shipka Pass, securing the Treaty of San Stefano and the liberation of Bulgaria from the Ottomans. The zemstvo system of local government was created during this ruler’s reign, which also included the sale of Alaska to the United States. This man was assassinated in St. Petersburg when a bomb was thrown into his carriage by the People’s Will. For ten points, name this Russian tsar who freed the serfs.",
        "answer": "Alexander II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1866, Alexander’s survival of an attack in St. Petersburg was commemorated by Viktor Hartmann, who sketched a “Great Gate” to be built in Kiev. While the gate was never built, the sketch inspired part of this Russian composer’s Pictures at an Exhibition.",
        "answer": "Modest Mussorgsky"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man became politically influenced by Craig Rodwell, a member of the Mattachine Society. Martin Blinder argued that the killer of this man was suffering from depression by using examples of the sugary foods he had recently been binging on. The “Twinkie defense” was employed by Dan White, who murdered this man and mayor George Moscone in 1978. For ten points, name this San Francisco politician, the first openly gay elected official in California.",
        "answer": "Harvey Bernard Milk"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "When Milk and Moscone were shot, the police were called by this San Francisco politician, who was at City Hall at the time and succeeded Moscone as mayor. This politician now serves as California’s senior senator.",
        "answer": "Dianne Feinstein"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "ThismanlostcredibilityduringtheDailyTelegraphaffair,inwhichhewascriticizedfordescribingthe English as “mad as March hares.” This man controversially ordered his troops to fight so that “no Chinese will ever again dare to look cross-eyed” at them during the Boxer Rebellion. During the July Crisis, this man sent a series of telegraphs to his cousin, Nicholas II, in an attempt to avoid the mobilization of their armies. For ten points, name this German Kaiser who ruled during World War I.",
        "answer": [
          "Wilhelm II",
          "William II,"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the July Crisis, Wilhelm was advised by this general, the head of the German Army. This man’s uncle was made a field marshal after his success in the Franco-Prussian War.",
        "answer": "Helmuth von Moltke the Younger"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Under the Natives Resettlement Act of 1954, this country’s government forced evictions in suburbs like Sophiatown. Many Indian laborers came on 25-year fixed contracts to this country’s city of Durban. This country’s province of Gauteng is home to the city of Vereeniging and a monument commemorating a group that engaged in the Great Trek. For ten points, name this country where Dutch settlers fought the British in the Boer Wars.",
        "answer": "South Africa"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Treaty of Vereeniging, ending the Second Boer War, was signed at the Melrose House in this other city in Gauteng province. This city, north of Johannesburg, is one of South Africa’s three capital cities.",
        "answer": "Pretoria"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A king with this name codified maritime law in the Book of the Consulate of the Sea and conquered Majorca from the Muslims. Walter Stewart conspired to kill a king of this name, and another king with this name took power after the Battle of Sauchieburn but lost the Battle of Flodden. The Glorious Revolution replaced a king of this name with William III. A king with this name faced the Gunpowder Plot and united the thrones of England and Scotland. For ten points, Queen Elizabeth I was succeeded by a king with what name?",
        "answer": [
          "James accept, but do not reveal, James I of Aragon",
          "James I of Scotland after “Walter”",
          "acceptJamesIVofScotlandafter“Sauchieburn”",
          "acceptJamesIIofEnglandafter“Glorious”",
          "James I of England after “Gunpowder”"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Consulate of the Sea was established in the 13th century in this Spanish kingdom under the rule of its James I. Later rulers of this monarchy included Ferdinand II, husband of Isabella of Castile.",
        "answer": "Aragon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In John Steinbeck’s East of Eden, Cyrus Trask makes a living telling lies about his role in this war. The historical fiction novel The Last Full Measure by Jeff Shaara ends a trilogy about this war that began with his father’s more famous work, The Killer Angels. Another story about this war describes Peyton Farquhar’s hanging at Owl Creek and was written by Ambrose Bierce. Stephen Crane’s The Red Badge of Courage describes Henry Fleming fighting in, for ten points, what war for the Union?",
        "answer": "American Civil War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another Ambrose Bierce work set in the Civil War is this short story about a young child’s horrifying experience in war. This short story is named for a bloody September 1863 battle in Georgia in which Bierce fought.",
        "answer": [
          "Chickamauga",
          "Battle of Chickamauga"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Mormons",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern-day state where the LDS Church has been headquartered since the mid-19th century.",
          "answer": "Utah"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of the LDS church who was killed with his brother Hyrum by a mob in 1844.",
          "answer": "Joseph Smith"
        },
        {
          "question": "State where those brothers were killed in Carthage after fleeing its town of Nauvoo.",
          "answer": "Illinois"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who took over church leadership from the slain founder, the namesake of a large Mormon university.",
          "answer": "Brigham Young"
        },
        {
          "question": "US President who sent federal troops to replace that man as territorial governor, launching the “Mormon War.”",
          "answer": "James Buchanan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Provisional US state proposed by Mormon settlers and unrecognized by the US government.",
          "answer": "State of Deseret"
        },
        {
          "question": "Massacre on the Baker-Fancher wagon train, in which over 100 civilians were killed by Mormon militia.",
          "answer": "Mountain Meadows Massacre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Court case that ruled against the use of religious duty as a criminal defense.",
          "answer": "Reynolds v. US The Polish Military"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Polish Military....",
      "prompt": "Name the the polish military.......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was overwhelmed by the Blitzkrieg at the start of what war?",
          "answer": "World War II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sought to prevent the country’s partitioning by what “great” tsarina of Russia?",
          "answer": [
            "Catherine the Great",
            "Catherine II"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Defeated what Germanic crusading order at the 1410 Battle of Grunwald?",
          "answer": [
            "Teutonic Knights or the Teutonic Order",
            "the Order of Brothers of the German House of Saint Mary in Jerusalem"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Faced the Khmelnytsky [kem-ill-nitz-kee] Uprising against what horseriding people based near the Don river?",
          "answer": "Cossacks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lifted a 1683 siege of what foreign capital city after the arrival of Jan III Sobieski’s hussars?",
          "answer": "Vienna"
        },
        {
          "question": "Had its officers targeted and buried in a mass grave in a forest in what 1940 massacre by the NKVD?",
          "answer": "Katyn Forest massacre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sent what officer, who died at the Siege of Savannah, to reform the American cavalry during the Revolutionary War?",
          "answer": "Casimir Pulaski"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sent what engineer of West Point to aid the American Revolution? He later led an uprising against Russia.",
          "answer": "Tadeusz Kosciuszko , but be lenient"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Malaysia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Malaysian capital city, which was captured by Japan in January 1942.",
          "answer": "Kuala Lumpur"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island that was expelled from the Federation of Malaysia in 1965.",
          "answer": "Singapore"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Prime Minister of that island city-state, who originally campaigned for Malaysian federation.",
          "answer": "Lee Kuan Yew"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island on which Malaysia borders Brunei, the former site of the Kingdom of Sarawak.",
          "answer": "Borneo"
        },
        {
          "question": "State-owned Malaysian oil company whose headquarters are in a namesake pair of 88-floor towers in the capital city.",
          "answer": [
            "Petronas",
            "Petronas Towers"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for the period from 1948-1960 in which British forces fought insurgent Malaysian guerrillas; it wasn’t called a war for insurance purposes.",
          "answer": "Malayan Emergency"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Prime Minister of independent Malaysia, who favored bumiputeras with affirmative action policies.",
          "answer": [
            "Tunku Abdul Rahman",
            "Tunku"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Current Prime Minister of Malaysia, who modernized the country in his first stint as leader from 1981-2003.",
          "answer": "Mahathir bin Mohamad"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After this battle, Moses Hazen accidentally threatened to hang Charles Asgill, causing an international ruckus. This battle’s losers failed to retreat to Gloucester Point and lost their supply line following the destruction of Thomas (20 pts)",
        "Graves’ fleet. In the aftermath of this battle, Charles O’Hara was told to give his sword to Benjamin Lincoln as the tune “The (10 pts)",
        "World Turned Upside Down” played. The Comte de Rochambeau helped trap a British force in, for ten points, what decisive battle of the Revolutionary War where Cornwallis surrendered?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Yorktown"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) When 38 people were killed by members of this organization who hijacked a bus on the Coastal Highway, Operation Litani was launched in response. A traffic collision in the Jabalia Refugee Camp prompted a war largely planned by (20 pts)",
        "factions of this group against another’s nation’s government. In that war, Abu Jihad organized youth militias in areas dominated by Fatah. As leader of this organization, (10 pts)",
        "Yasser Arafat signed the Oslo Accords, securing greater autonomy for the Gaza Strip. For ten points, name this militant nationalist organization that advocates for an Arab nation in what is now Israel."
      ],
      "answer": "Palestine Liberation Organization"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler commissioned Comte de la Perouse’s failed circumnavigation of the world, and his admiral Pierre de Suffren allied the Mysores against England. This monarch, who appointed Charles de Calonne as Finance Minister two years after dismissing (20 pts)",
        "Jacques Necker, reversed the Edict of Fontainebleau to grant religious freedom in the Edict of Versailles. Members of the (10 pts)",
        "Third Estate united in a tennis court during the reign of, for ten points, what French king who married Marie Antoinette and was guillotined in the French Revolution?"
      ],
      "answer": "Louis XVI"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A theorem regarding this process demonstrated that it cannot satisfy all three criteria of non-dictatorship, independence of irrelevant alternatives, and Pareto efficiency; that theorem about this process is (20 pts)",
        "Arrow’s Impossibility Theorem. A method of running this process is named for Condorcet. As a territory, Wyoming was the first state to allow (10 pts)",
        "women to participate in this process in 1869. For ten points, name this civic process in which individual preferences are counted to determine an outcome, like choosing a Congressperson."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "voting systems",
        "elections and other equivalents",
        "word forms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A legislator in this state, E. H. Hurst, murdered Herbert Lee but was acquitted by an all-white jury; one witness to that murder, Louis Allen, was initially forced to lie, then murdered for telling the truth to federal investigators. While participating in Freedom (20 pts)",
        "Summer, three CORE workers were abducted and killed in this state while leaving Neshoba County. The murder and open casket funeral of (10 pts)",
        "Emmett Till, a teenage boy killed in this state, sparked outrage in 1955. For ten points, name this state where Medgar Evers was assassinated in his home in Jackson."
      ],
      "answer": "Mississippi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a parody of this show on Cheers, Cliff Clavin complains that Cary Grant really had never been in his kitchen. An SNL skit parodying this show featured Tom Hanks playing a MAGA hat-wearing character who bonds with Kenan Thompson, playing the (20 pts)",
        "host. In another take on this show, H&R Block, not FedEx, was a correct answer that ended a (10 pts)",
        "74-game winning streak on this show in 2004. Art Fleming originally hosted this show, which removed its five-win cap in 2003 before Ken Jennings’ record run. For ten points, name this syndicated game show hosted by Alex Trebek."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Jeopardy!",
        "Black Jeopardy!"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A prime minister of this country failed in a re-election campaign after environmental activists protested in the Franklin Dam controversy. Another prime minister claimed that “the real life of this nation [...] cannot be found in petty gossip of so-called fashionable suburbs” in a speech addressed to the (20 pts)",
        "“Forgotten People;” that longest-serving prime minister of this country was Robert Menzies. Kevin (10 pts)",
        "Rudd and Julia Gillard are among the past leaders of its Labour Party, which opposes its Liberal Party. For ten points, name this country where, in 2018, Scott Morrison replaced Malcolm Turnbull as Prime Minister in Canberra."
      ],
      "answer": "Australia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The prisoners of this region’s Syrets conentration camp were forced to cover up a massacre by burning corpses. In September 1941, Kurt Eberhard ordered the executions of over 30,000 Jews and well over 100,000 people total in this region’s capital city. The (20 pts)",
        "Babi Yar massacre took place in what is now this country, where the city of Pripyat was (10 pts)",
        "evacuated in 1986 and labeled an “Exclusion Zone” after a nuclear disaster at Chernobyl. For ten points, name this former Soviet country where atrocities of the Holocaust took place near Kiev."
      ],
      "answer": "Ukraine"
    }
  ]
}